Juan Navarrete y Guerrero collection, 1912-2000 (bulk 1948-2000)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Juan Navarrete y Guerrero collection, 1912-2000
MS 423
Juan Navarrete y Guerrero
Papers, 1912-2000 (bulk 1948-2000). This collection contains materials relating to Bishop Juan Navarrete y Guerrero of the diocese of Hermosillo, Sonora. Items include biographical materials; printed materials including newsletters and pamphlets; audio materials; and photographic materials including photographs, slides, and postcards. The bulk of the material is a nearly complete set of the El Católico newsletter (1948-2000) and over thirty of Navarrete y Guerrero's recorded sermons. All materials are in Spanish.
10 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Biographical Note
Juan Navarrete y Guerrero was born in 1886 in Oaxaca, Mexico. He began his studies at the Seminary Church of León, Guanajuato. In 1904 he traveled to Rome to continue his studies at the Colegio Pío Latino Americano de Roma. He earned his doctorate of theology in 1909 from the Pontificia Universidad Gregoriana. That same year he returned to Aguascalientes, Mexico an ordained priest. In 1916 he founded various Catholic organizations including the Acción Católica de la Juventud Mexicana (A.C.J.M.) which was later active in the Cristero Movement. In 1919 he was ordained bishop of Sonora at only 32 years of age, becoming the world's youngest bishop.
In 1926 Navarrete y Guerrero was exiled to Arizona as a result of the anti-Catholic persecution implemented by President Plutarco Calles. During this time he became involved in the Cristero Movement which was a rebellion against the anti-Catholic stance of the Mexican government. Navarrete y Guerrero returned to Sonora in 1929 but three years later, in 1932, a warrant was issued for his arrest and he was subsequently exiled again for five years. In 1937 he returned to Sonora after the new governor granted him amnesty.
Upon his return to the Sonoran Diocese, he began to help rebuild the Catholic community that had suffered during the Cristero Movement. Throughout the 1940s to the 1960s he was instrumental in founding hospitals, orphanages, and over fifty Catholic schools. In 1959 the Diocese of Sonora was divided in two: the Diocese of Hermosillo and the Diocese of Cuidad Obregón and in 1964, Navarrete y Guerrero was appointed the first archbishop of Hermosillo. He retired four years later and was soon after appointed Titular Archbishop of Vulturaria. He died in February of 1982, at the age of ninety-five.
Organization
This collection is organized into 6 series
Series I: Biographical Files, 1964-1969
Series II: Subject Files, 1936-1969
Series III: Printed Materials, 1948-2000
Series IV: Photographic Materials, 1912-1977
Series V: Audio Materials, 1948-1994
Series VI: Oversize, 1986-1989
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1912-2000 (bulk 1948-2000). This collection contains materials relating to Bishop Juan Navarrete y Guerrero of the diocese of Hermosillo, Sonora. Materials include; Navarrete y Guerrero biographies, community histories of the Sonoran Diocese, a nearly complete set of the El Católico newsletter (1948-2000), over thirty of Navarrete y Guerrero's recorded sermons, recordings of religious songs, as well as recorded sermons and lectures by others, photographs of Navarrete y Guerrero and members of the Sonoran Diocese including the El Católico staff, and slide sets of La Tierra Santa (The Holy Land) and the Vatican. All materials are in Spanish.
Related Material
de la Torre Family Papers, (1874-1994), MS 420
Access Terms
Navarrete y Guerrero, Juan, 1886-1982 -- Archives.
Bishops -- Mexico -- Sonora (State) -- Biography.
Catholic Church -- Bishops -- Biography.
Catholic Church. Diocese of Hermosillo (Mexico).
Catholic Church. Diocese of Sonora -- History.
Sonora (Mexico: State).
Container List
- Biographical Files. 1964-1969
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains biographical information on Juan Navarrete y Guerrero. One biography also includes a brief history of the Sonoran Diocese. All materials in this series are in Spanish.
  - Navarrete y Guerrero, Juan History – El Semenario Perseguido 1932-1937. undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Navarrete y Guerrero, Juan History (album recuerdo) – Juan Navarrete y Guerrero. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Navarrete y Guerrero, Juan and Sonoran Diocese History – Esfuerzo. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Subject Files. 1936-1969
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains a handwritten newsletter, El Gran Cues., from 1936, an incomplete set of martyr cards relating the biographical and historical information of Mexican martyrs mostly from the 1920's and 30's, and two documents regarding the community of Sonora: Sonora a su Reina y Madre, an "album recuerdo" pertaining to the history of the Diocese of Sonora and Distinguidas personas desaparecidas de la vida sonorense which contains brief biographical information on notable deceased citizens of Hermosillo, Sonora. All Subject Files materials are in Spanish.
  - El Gran Cues. Periódico Semenal. 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mexican Martyrs. undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sonora Community History. 1938-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Printed Materials. 1948-2000
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains newsletters and pamphlets. The bulk of the series is a nearly complete set of the religious newsletter, El Católico, published by the Diocese of Hermosillo, Sonora. The remainder of the series consists of three religious pamphlets. All Printed Materials are in Spanish. Note: Some materials are located in Series VI: Oversize Materials.
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1990 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1991 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1992 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1993 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1995 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1996 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1997 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1998 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 1999 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Newsletters – El Católico. 2000 (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - Newsletters – La Cruz. 1968 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters – Iglesia Católica de San Juan Evangelista. 1999 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Pamphlets – Primera Ultreya Mundial Roma 1966 Resumen de Vivencias. 1966 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Pamphlets – La Provocación de los Jesuitas y del Clero Político. 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Pamphlets – Tu cita con Dios: La Misa (Liturgy). 1965 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Photographic Materials. 1912-1977
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains photographs of Navarrete y Guerrero and photographs of members of the Sonoran Diocese including the El Católico staff. Also included are two travel souvenir slide collections of La Tierra Santa (the Holy Land) and the Vatican. Among the postcards is a marked postcard with the writing of Navarrete y Guerrero. The text within this series is in Spanish.
  - Photographs – General. 1912-1977 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Photographs – Navarrete y Guerrero, Juan. undated, 1963-1970 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Postcards. undated, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Slides - La Tierra Santa. undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Slides – Souvenirs of the Vatican. undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Audio Materials. 1948-1994
  This series contains over thirty of Juan Navarrete y Guerrero's sermons (1948-1960). The original copies, recorded on cassette tapes, will be transferred to CD format for public use. Other audio materials include religious songs as well as other speakers' sermons and lectures. The tapes not transferred to CD, located in Box 6, have been arranged alphabetically by title. All audio materials are in Spanish.
  - Charla familiar de jueves-Caridad. Navarrete, Juan. 1950 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señores. Día I. Navajoa, Sonora. Navarrete, Juan. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señores. Día II. Navarrete, Juan. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Conferencia. Día III. Navarrete, Juan. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señores. Día IV. Navarrete, Juan. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señores. Día V. Navarrete, Juan. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Bendición de la Capilla del Oasis. Navarrete, Juan. 1953 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - La exigencia de vestir honestamente en la Iglesia. Navarrete, Juan. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Misa de Bonda. Celebración del Santo Matrimonio. Navarrete, Juan. 1950 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Padre nuestro. Venga a nosostros Tu reino. Navarrete, Juan. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Descuido y Omisiones. Navarrete, Juan. undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Misa de media noche. Acción de gracias. Navarrete, Juan. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Festividad de Navidad. Navarrete, Juan. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Navidad. Fin de año. Sermon de lo misa gallo. Navarrete, Juan. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señoras. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señoras. Iglesia. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señoras. Castidad. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señoras Moralidad.. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Ejercicios Cuaresmales para Señoras Justicia Social.. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Abusos en el culto. Devoción a los Santos. Navarrete, Juan. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón de la institución. Navarrete, Juan. undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón de la institución. Navarrete, Juan. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón de la institución. Navarrete, Juan. 2nd copy. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón de la institución. Navarrete, Juan. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón de la institución. Navarrete, Juan. 2nd copy. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón del mandato. Navarrete, Juan. undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Jueves santo. Sermón del mandato. Navarrete, Juan. 2nd copy. undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Jueves santo. Oración del Huerto. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Jueves santo. Oración del Huerto. Navarrete, Juan. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Jueves santo. Eucaristia y sacerdocio. Navarrete, Juan. 1952 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Viernes Santo. Sermón de Pésame. Navarrete, Juan. 1953 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Viernes Santo. Sermón de Pésame. Navarrete, Juan. 1949 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Viernes Santo. Sermón de Pésame. Navarrete, Juan. 1948 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Padre, que todos sean uno. Sermón CUM Hermosillo.. Talavera, Carlos. 1975 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - El amor de Cristo nos urge. Montaño, Hugo. undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Bienaventuerados los pobres de Espíritu. Cepeda, Oneismo. undated (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - La evangelización portadora de la paz, "Reciben Shalom." Betancourt, Dario. undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - María en las Escrituras. Betancourt, Dario. undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - ¿Por qué estoy enfermo?. Betancourt, Dario. undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - "Los sacramentos", Fuente de Sanción.. Betancourt, Dario. undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Capilla del Carmen.. Lazaro. 1994 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Sed de agua viva.. Cordova, Jorge. undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Presencia de la Virgen en el mundo. Cordova, Jorge. undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - El Espíritu Santo y María. Cordova, Jorge. undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - La Iglesia Catolica y las sectas Protestantes. Amatuli, Flaviano. undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - La Iglesia Catolica y las sectas Protestantes. Amatuli, Flaviano. 2nd copy. undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Vida de fraternidad – III. Exigencias Fraternas. Larrañaga, Ignacio. undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Vivir en el Espíritu Santo.. Segundo, Cano F. undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - El Don de Dios. Segundo, Cano F. undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Volver al Dios que nos ama. Renovación. Segundo, Cano F. 1991 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Volver al Dios que nos ama. Renovación. Segundo, Cano F. 2nd copy. 1991 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - El Padre promote enviar al Espíritu Santo. Segundo, Cano F. 1991 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Teología fundamental. Ponce. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - El Rosario, desde el punto de vista terapéutico y spiritual. De Jesús Bucio, Eduardo. undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Side A:Cristo, centro de la historia. Mateo, Marcos, Lucas y Juan. Side B: Cristo anuncia Un mundo nuevo. Sociedad Bíblica Católica Nac. De México. undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Side A:Aspecto humano-divino de la Sociedad Fundada por Cristo. Side B: Mientras Cristo Regresa. Sociedad Bíblica Católica Nac. De México. undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Los sacramentos. Side A:Las ordenes sagradas. Side B: El matrimonio. undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Side A:Dios llama a Abraham (Génesis). Colección circulo Biblico. Side B: La alianza de Dios con Israel (Exodo). Sociedad Bíblica Católica Nac. De México. undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Side A:En marcha hacia la tierra prometida. Side B: Israel se establece en Caneen. Sociedad Bíblica Católica Nac. De México. undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Side A:Los profetas señalan el pedcado y el catigo de Israel. Side B: El perdón y la espera del mesias. Sociedad Bíblica Católica Nac. De México. undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - María, estrella, de la evangelización. Sevillano, Lino. undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Oración de la noche. Ruiz, Blanca. undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Un poco más. Venid a mi los que esteis fatigados por la carga, que yo os aliviare. Ruiz, Blanca. undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Le llave de oro de la sanación el perdon. Ruiz, Blanca. undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Un poco más. Venid a mi los que esteis fatigados por la carga, que yo os aliviare. Ruiz, Blanca. 2nd copy. undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - De la renovación encuentro en el CUM. Ruiz, Blanca. undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - El amor de Jesus reconstruye las relaciones Familiares. Sangiovani, María. undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - El amor de Jesus reconstruye las relaciones Familiares. Sangiovani, María. undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Side A: Los sacramentos en general. Side B: El bautismo y la confirmación. undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Los sacramentos. Side A: La penitencia. Side B: La extrema Unción. undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Side A: Del credo-La creación de los Angeles. Side B: Creación y caída del hombre. undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Side A: Del credo-El Espíritu Santo y la gracia. Side B: Del credo-La santa Iglesia Católico. undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Side A: Del credo-Dios y sus perfecciones. Side B: Del credo-La santísima Trinidad. undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Side A: Del credo-La Com. de los Santos. Side B: La Resurrección y la vida Sempiterna. undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Side A: Los mandamientos en general. Side B: Los mandamientos de la Iglesia. undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - El primer mandamiento de la ley de Dios. undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Side A: Segundo y tercer mandates de la ley de Dios. Side B: El cuarto mandamiento de la ley de Dios. undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Side A: El quinto mandamiento de la ley de Dios. Side B: El octavo mandamiento de la ley de Dios. undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Side A: Sexto y novena mandamientos de la ley de Dios. Side B: Séptimo y décimo mandamientos de la ley de Dios. undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - El santo sacrificio de la misa. undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - La Sagrada Eucaristía. undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Side A: La muerte de Cristo es nuestra liberación (Mateo, Marcos, Lucas y Juan). Side B: La resurrección de Cristo es prenda de Nuestra immortalidad. undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
  - La confianza en Dios y en María logra Maravillas. Marychel y Fernando. undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - Predeicación. Lázaro, Ma. undated (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Visita del delegado apostolic cena. Navarrete, Juan y Lopez Legaz. 1960 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - El Amor de Dios Tema II de la Renovación. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Side A: Cantos de Misa. Side B: Cantos de Mensaje y Recreativos. undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cantos de la misa con guitarras. undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Coro de la Capilla de Santa Eduwiges. undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Side A: del Credo, La Encarnación (La Navidad). Side B: del Credo La Redención. undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ex-Testigo de Jehova. Antonio Carrea. undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - La eucaristia, vida de unidad con Cristo y los hermanos. P.J. Córdova. Encuentro en Phoenix. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - La eucaristia y los jóvenes.Guillermo Valencia. Encuentro en Phoenix. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Huesos secos. Salvador Gómez. undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - La intimidad. Caso 8 años. undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - María Intercesora. Jesús también puede cambiar nuestra agua en vino. undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Me abandonaron a mí, fuente de agua viva. P. Andrés Dávila Encuentro en Los Angeles. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Mi Cristo roto, de Ramón Cué, S.J. Voz de José Antonio Cossio. undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Monje trapense. Rafael su vida, sus escritos. No. 011 – No. 022. undated (Box 6, Folder 14-25)
  - Pensando en Dios. Cantos de Renovación. undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Side A: El Rosario, desde el punto de vista Terapéutico y espiritual. Eduardo de Jesús Bucio. Side B: Las Quince Promesa undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Testimonio de Vicky Davis. "Yo soy el pan de vida". Encuentro en Phoenix. 1991 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - En Tierra Santa. undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - A la vuelta al mundo en 80 ritmos. undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Oversize. 1986-1989
  This series contains an oversize item from the Printed Materials series: En Marcha, a religious newsletter from Hermosillo, Sonora. All materials are in Spanish.
  - Printed Materials: Newsletters – En Marcha. 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Printed Materials: Newsletters – En Marcha. 1987 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Printed Materials: Newsletters – En Marcha. 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Printed Materials: Newsletters – En Marcha. 1989 (Box 7, Folder 4)